<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To all the affectors and approvers in England of the London petition of the eleventh of September, 1648, but especially to the owners of it, by their subscriptions, either to it, or any other petition in the behalf of it; and particularly to the first promoters of it, my true friends, the citizens of London, &amp;c. (continuing unshaken in their principles, by offices, places, or other base bribes or rewards) usually meeting at the Whalbone in Lothbury, behinde the Royal Exchange, commonly (but most unjustly) stiled Levellers.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2183A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220125</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831553</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831553</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36016</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48481)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36016)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2050:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To all the affectors and approvers in England of the London petition of the eleventh of September, 1648, but especially to the owners of it, by their subscriptions, either to it, or any other petition in the behalf of it; and particularly to the first promoters of it, my true friends, the citizens of London, &amp;c. (continuing unshaken in their principles, by offices, places, or other base bribes or rewards) usually meeting at the Whalbone in Lothbury, behinde the Royal Exchange, commonly (but most unjustly) stiled Levellers.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>17 of July, 1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 8: John Lilburne.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from from Wing; imprint date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Christ Church Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Levellers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36016:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To all the Affectors and Approvers in <hi>England,</hi> of the
<hi>London</hi> Petition of the eleventh of <hi>September, 1648.</hi> but
especially to the owners of it, by their ſubſcriptions, either to it, or
any other Petition in the behalf of it; and particularly to the firſt
promoters of it, my true Friends, the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c.
(continuing unſhaken in their principles, by Offices, Places, or other baſe
bribes or rewards) uſually meeting at the <hi>Whalbone</hi> in
<hi>Lothbury,</hi> behinde the Royal Exchange, commonly (but moſt unjustly)
ſtiled Levellers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen, and worthy Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the ſaying of the Spirit of God, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.17.
<hi>That a friend loveth at all times, and a brother is born for
adverſity.</hi> And <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.24. <hi>There is a friend that
ſticketh cloſer then a brother;</hi> the laſt of which ſayings, I am
able by experience to ſeal to the truth of; and even amongſt you, I have
found ſome, that in the burning heat of the day of my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, have
ſtuck cloſer to me, then my brother; which was not onely largely
manifeſted by your Petitioning for me, when I was priſoner in
<hi>Newgate,</hi> about four yeers ago, and by your effectual Petitioning for
me laſt year, which was the inſtrumental means of my deliverance out of an
almoſt three years captivity; But alſo your late unwearied pains taken for
me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in divers Petitions of a hazardous nature at the beginning
of my preſent captivity; which though fruitleſs in themſelves, as to my
liberty, yet are ſtrong demonſtrations of the continuance of your zealous
affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to me in particular, and to the Liberties of the Land of your
nativity; for which I ſuffer, and am in bonds.</p>
            <p>But hearing that you had ſome thoughts of new motions for me,
and my fellow-pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, I judg it a fit opportunity for me, to viſit you
with a few lines, and to acquaint you how things at preſent ſtand with me.
I beleeve the moſt of you have ſeen, if not read my late Book of the eight
of <hi>June,</hi> 1649. Intituled, <hi>The legal fundamental Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the
people of</hi> England, <hi>revived, aſſerted, and vindicated, in which,
from the</hi> 43. <hi>page to the</hi> 59. <hi>page.</hi> I have fully, both by
Law and Reaſon, undeniably, and unanſwerably proved, <hi>That the preſent
Juncto ſitting at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>are no Parliament at all, in any
ſenſe, either upon the principles of Law, or Reaſon, but are a company of
uſurping Tyrants, and deſtroyers of your Laws, Liberties, Freedoms, and
Properties,</hi> ſitting by vertue of the power, and conqueſt of the Sword;
from whom, if we will believe their Oracle Mr. <hi>John Cook, we may, and
ought, if we can, to deliver our ſelves.</hi> His words in the Kings Caſe
ſtated <hi>page</hi> 10. are, <hi>That all people that live at the beck, and
nod of Tyrannical men, may and ought to free themſelves from that Tyranny,
if, and when they can; for ſuch Tyrants, that ſo domineer with a rod of
Iron, do not govern by Gods permiſſive hand of approbation or benediction,
but by the permiſſive hand of his providence, ſuffering them to ſcourge
the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for ends beſt known unto himſelf, until he open a way for the
people to work out their own infranchiſements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in <hi>page</hi> 22. (ſaith he) <hi>Conqueſt onely makes
title amongſt Wolves, and Bears, but not amongſt men:</hi> And in
<hi>page</hi> 8. <hi>That a man ruling by Luſt, and not by Law, is a Creature
that was never of Gods making, nor of Gods approbation, but his permiſsion;
and though ſuch men are ſaid to be gods on Earth, its in no other
ſenſe, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Devil is called,
the god of this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame Note alſo the great men of the Army ſing, in their
late Remonſtrance from Saint <hi>Albans, Novemb.</hi> 16. 1648. <hi>p.</hi>
48. 67. and in <hi>page</hi> 22. they ſay <hi>That when a Magiſtrate
intruſted with a power to protect and preſerve the peoples R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ghts and Liberties, ſhall riſe to
the aſſuming hurtful powers, which he never had committed to him, and
indeed, to take away all thoſe foundations of Right and Liberty, and of
redreſs, or remedy too, which <pb n="2" facs="tcp:36016:2"/>the people have reſerved
from him, and to ſwallow up all into his own abſolute will and power, to
impoſe or take away, yea, to deſtroy at pleaſure; and declaring all
appeal herein, to the eſtabliſhed equal Judgment, or to any other Judgment
of men at all, ſhall flie to the way of Fame, upon the truſting people</hi>
(which both <hi>Cromwel</hi> and <hi>Ireton, &amp;c.</hi> have already, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> really done, as ever the King did,)
<hi>and by it attempt to uphold and eſtabliſh himſelf in that abſolute
tyrannical power, ſo aſſumed over them; and in the exerciſe thereof at
pleaſure, ſuch a perſon in ſo doing, does forfeit all that truſt and
power he had, and abſolve the people thereby, from the Bonds and Covenant of
Peace betwixt him and them; does ſet them free to take their beſt
advantage, and (if he fall within their power) to proceed in judgment againſt
him, even for that alone if there were no more;</hi> of all which, in the evil
part of it, in the higheſt, the chief Authors of that <hi>Remonſtrance</hi>
are guilty: <hi>Therefore out of thy own mouth will I judg thee, thou wicked
ſervant, ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th Chriſt,
Luke</hi> 19.22. And ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to his, <hi>One of themſelves,
even a Prophet of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir own ſaid;
The Cretians are always liers, evil Beaſts, ſlow Bellies: this witneſs is
true; therefore—&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I ſay, conſidering that which is before declared, I cannot
upon any terms in the world, either with ſafety, juſtice or conſcience,
as things ſtand with me at preſent, give my conſent, but hinder as much
as I am able, all addreſſes from you or any others for me, that ſhall own
thoſe uſurping Tyrants as a Parliament, eſpecially by Petition <hi>Which
was a courſe</hi> (ſaith the pretended Parliament Solicitor againſt the
King, in his Caſe ſtated, <hi>page</hi> 24.) <hi>which Gods people did not
take with</hi> Rehoboam, <hi>for they never Petitioned him</hi> (although he
was their lawful and ſupreme Magiſtrate) <hi>but adviſed him; he
refuſing their counſel, and hearkened to young and wicked Counſellors,
and they cry out, To thy Tents O Iſrael, and made quick and ſhort work of
it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhall rather deſire and adviſe you; by Letter like
your ſelves, addreſs your ſelves to the Lord <hi>Fairfax;</hi> by the
ſword of whom and his Souldiers, I am now in priſon for my honeſty and
innocency, and nothing elſe, and demand my liberty of him; if he refuſe,
print it, and do as God, and Reaſon ſhall direct you; for it was his and
his Souldiers force that fetcht me out of my Bed, the 28 of <hi>March,</hi>
1649. without all ſhadow of Law or Juſtice, <hi>and againſt the tenor of
all their own Declarations;</hi> the particular pages of which, you may read in
my following Letter to Mr. <hi>Holland, page</hi> 5. And by force of Arms,
carryed me to <hi>whitehal,</hi> and then to <hi>Derby</hi> houſe, before a
company of men, that in Law had no more power to commit my body to priſon,
then ſo many theeves and robbers up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Suiters</hi> Hill have; who by the
Rules of their own wills <hi>(as in the ſecond Edition of the Picture of
them, I have fully declared)</hi> ſent me by force of Arms to the Tower; for
all my ſhort eternity in this world.</p>
            <p>But I intreat you ſeriouſly to conſider that I cannot
adviſe you to make addreſs to him, as the General of the Nations forces,
for he is no ſuch thing; but is meerly a great Tyrant, ſtanding by the
power of his own will, and a ſtrong ſword, born by his vaſſals,
ſlaves and creatures having no commiſſion to be General, <hi>either from
Law, the Parliament, or from the prime Laws of Nature and Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Firſt, when he was firſt made General by both Houſes of
Parliament, it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly againſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he letter of the Law, which action
cannot be juſtified, either before God or man, but in caſe of extream
neceſſity; and for the accompliſhment of a univerſall righteous end,
<hi>viz. The redeeming, ſetling, and ſecuring the peoples rational and
juſt Rights and Freedoms,</hi> and not in the leaſt, for ſetting up any
particular ſelviſh or factious intereſt.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, in refuſing to disband, &amp;c he hath rebelled
againſt his Parliament com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and thereby deſtroyed and
annihilated it; And at <hi>New-Market Heath, the fifth of June</hi> 1647 betook
himſelf to the prime Laws of Nature, and by common conſent of his Officers
and Souldiers became their General, <hi>and entred into a ſolemn and mutuall
ingagement before God, and one another,</hi> for the accompliſhment of
thoſe righteous ends <pb n="3" facs="tcp:36016:2"/>therein contained, for the good of the
Kingdom and themſelves, by ſubſcribing his name, or at leaſt expreſly
aſſenting thereunto, and approving thereof with ſolemn ingagement, as is
at large Printed in the Armies Book of Declarations, <hi>p.</hi> 23, 24, 25,
26. by the very letter of which, he, nor his Officers could not govern the Army
jointly or ſeverally, by the former Rules or Articles of Martiall Law, <hi>no
nor ſo much as make an Officer of the meaneſt quality, nor put forth any
publike Declaration, nor treat with, nor conclude with any in reference to the
Army, but by the joynt advice and approbation of their new erected and
eſtabliſhed councel of Adjutators,</hi> which for order and methods ſake,
the General was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted to convene and call together, as the King formerly
was Parliaments, or the Lord Mayor of <hi>London</hi> Common Councels; and yet
notwithſtanding he and his Officers, like a generation of moſt perfidious,
falſe, and faithleſs men, broke all this ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to pieces, within
leſs then twenty dayes after it was made, and ſo annihilated and
deſtroyed his power, authority, or commiſſion, flowing from the conſent
of the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, before he had really accompliſhed any one thing, he, or
they ingaged for, and hath ſince two ſeverall times, put a nullity, or
force, upon his originall Creators, Lords and Maſters, the Parliament.</p>
            <p>And that he and his Officers broke their forementioned ſolemn
ingagements in ſo ſhort a time; I prove fully out of their own book of
Declarations, in which <hi>page</hi> 36. to 46 <hi>I finde a Declaration, dated
the</hi> 14. <hi>of June,</hi> 1647. <hi>made and publiſhed by his Excellency
Sir</hi> Thomas Fairfax, <hi>with the Officers and Souldiers of his Army;</hi>
(mark it well) for in the very words of it, it is, in Excellency worth all the
Declarations that ever the Army made ſince: and in <hi>page</hi> 47. to 50.
<hi>I finde a generall charge againſt the eleven Members, with a paper
delivered with it to the Parliaments Commiſſioners at St.</hi> Albans,
<hi>the</hi> 17. <hi>June</hi> 1647 <hi>by the appointment of his Excellency
Sir</hi> T. Fairfax, <hi>and the Soldiers of the Army under his command;</hi>
but in the following <hi>pages, viz pag.</hi> 51, 52, 53, 54. I finde that the
21, 22, 25. of June, 1647. his <hi>Excellency, and his Councel of War
alone,</hi> without the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Adjutators, repreſenting the Souldiers,
according to their ingagement, writ letters to, and entered into a Treaty with
the Lord Mayor and Common-Councel of <hi>London, which was a baſe,
perfidious, treacherous act, and an abſolute breach of their ſolemn
ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> yea in <hi>page</hi> 57. <hi>June</hi> 23. 1647. The General,
and twenty eight Grandee, and creature Officers, publiſh a Remonſtrance to
the Kingdom, and that in the name of the Army; in which baſe and abominable
apoſtacie they continued, without ever wiping their mouths, or recanting what
they had ſo unjuſtly done, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he whole tenor of their Book of Declarations doth declare; yea when
the particular charge againſt the eleven Members comes from them, it comes
onely in the name of the General and his Councel of War, <hi>page</hi> 94. yea,
and all this, with ten times more (as I beleeve the world will ſhortly and
fully ſee) <hi>was done in despite of the Adjutators, or conſent of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>giments, Troops, or Companies;</hi> for all thoſe two grand and
lying Apoſtates (<hi>Corn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi>
Den. <hi>and Parſon</hi> John Can, <hi>a late cheat at Amſterdam</hi>)
confident affirmations to the contrary in their late Printed lying books,
intituled the <hi>Levellers</hi> Deſign <hi>page</hi> 4. 5. and the ſecond
part of the Diſcoverer, <hi>page.</hi> 5 6. where they av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, <hi>That the councel of Adjutators,
eſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
ſolemn ingagement, was d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſolved and made null by the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me power by which they had their conſtitution; and that it was
done by a Petition to the Generall from moſt of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp;c.</hi>
But although I iudg the two <hi>forementioned lying baſe Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes,</hi> to be ſo abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minably vile,
that I judg not my excrements mean enough upon equal terms to ballance
againſt them; yet knowing the affairs of the Army then ſo extrraordinarily
well as I do, I will ballance life againſt life, that neither they, nor any
man breathing can produce a Petition ſo much as from one ſingle Troop or
Company, <hi>much leſs from a Regiment,</hi> and therefore much leſs from
the greateſt part of the Regiments, both of Horſe and Foot, for calling
home their Adjutators, before the Gen. and his Officers had, as is before
mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <pb n="4" facs="tcp:36016:3"/>
               <hi>broke in pieces the ſolemn engagement again
and again</hi> (and Invaſion of Rights and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges was the true declared
ground and cauſe of all the late wars with the late beheaded King, and is
really the originall ground of moſt (if not all) the cruell wars in the
world) But if the Souldiers had made ſuch a Petition (which they never did)
it were not much materiall I think, for they ingaged ſomething to and for the
Kingdom, in reference to the ſetlement of their Liberties and Freedoms, whith
I am ſure they in no one title ever accompliſhed or performed, and
therefore till that be done, they can not rationally or juſtly abſolve
themſelves from the true intent or meaning of that engagement.</p>
            <p>But I wiſh thoſe Champions for lies and Apoſtaſie, would
inſtance the place where, the time when, and the Regiments that
ſubſcribed and delivered ſuch a Petition, and deal ingeniouſly with the
world, whether it were a free act, or a compulſive one, wrought
<hi>underhand, by all the ſnares, pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cies, tricks, gins, and ſlights, that poſſible the Officers
could invent, without or b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>low a
viſible and compulſive force,</hi> which can never of right unty that knot;
Sure I am, divers of the Adiutators, &amp;c. ſent ſeverall complaints to
me, &amp;c. to the Tower from St. <hi>Albans;</hi> immediatly after the
ſolemn ingagement was made, <hi>complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that Cromwel, Ireton,
&amp;c.</hi> (one of which two pen'd this engagement) <hi>would needs
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by force and frowns totally
break and diſſolve it;</hi> of which baſeneſs (though then we we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e not viſibly faln out) I told
<hi>Cromwel</hi> very freely and plainly of, as appears by my Letters to him of
the 22 of <hi>June,</hi> 1647 and the 1 of <hi>July</hi> 1647. and in my
Adviſe to the Adiutators of the 16 of <hi>July,</hi> 1647. All which I
cauſed immediatly after to be Printed in my Book, <hi>called</hi> Jonahs
<hi>cries out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hales
belly,</hi> and the like in my little Book, <hi>called the Jugl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcovered;</hi> and I am ſure it was <hi>Auguſt</hi> following,
when the Armies Head quarters were at <hi>Kingſton,</hi> where
<hi>Cromwel</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gun to be afraid
of the Adiutators ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending his underhand and night Juglings with the King,
<hi>to make himſelf able, like cardinal</hi> Woolſey, <hi>to ſay, I and
my K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng;</hi> which he was afraid
the Adiutators ſhould take too much notice of, although long before their
power and authority was deſtroyed; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was not willing they
ſhould at all remain or lodge at the Head-quarters, although <hi>Crumwel</hi>
had weeks, and ſome moneths before deſignedly, and of ſet purpoſe, with
all his power and intereſt, walked in a continual breaking and trampling the
engagement under his feet, and therefore about that time he and his agents
ſet that Petition a foot, to rid the Head quarters of the Adiutators, that
they might not ſo much as ſee his baſeneſs but alas, that Petition
could not null and deſtroy that that was broken, nuld in efficacy and power,
annihilated long before, but yet I could not for all this ever hear that
Petition was one tenth part ſo formall as they report it to be.</p>
            <p>But from what hath been already ſaid, (and in time will
ſpeedily be declared) <hi>it is evident that the General and the Officers at
St.</hi> Albans <hi>broke their ſolemn engagement with their Souldiers and
the Kingdom, immediatly after it was mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and tyrannicall, and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly invaded their Rights and
Freedoms,</hi> which bred heart-burnings, and thoſe diviſions which the
publique enemy (ſo called) took the advantage of, and ſo came on the wars;
God ever after their abominable and villanous appoſtacy, filling their hands
with trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and confuſions, beſides loſs of reputation and good name,
upon whoſe ſcore alone lies the true guilt of all the blood-ſhed in the
laſt years war, and of all the miſeries that ſince have befaln
<hi>Ireland</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Which they might eaſily have
relieved, if they had pleaſed, with thoſe forces they disbanded in
ſeveral places of the Nation, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after the making the foreſaid
Engagement; or with thoſe twenty they the laſt Spring disbanded, out of
every Troop and Company: Part of which, in diſcontent at their baſe uſing
of them, run to <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ghorn</hi>
and <hi>Poyer,</hi> and others; to <hi>Goring, Cavel,</hi> and others, to Sir
<hi>Marmaduke La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gdale,</hi> and the
Scots: but <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> it ſeems was reſolved then, That no forces
ſhould go to relieve <hi>Ireland,</hi> till he went with them, with an
abſolute Commiſſion to be King of <hi>Ireland:</hi> Which Commiſſion,
though he hath got, yet he may fail of his expected Town, both there and
elſewhere.</note> and this year again is likely, by forraign invaſions of
ſtrange Nations, and by inteſtine broyles to befall <hi>England;</hi> and
therefore if you <pb n="5" facs="tcp:36016:3"/>love the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> tell him,
that though people at the preſent deal by him and <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> &amp;c.
as the Parliament uſed to do with the King, <hi>laying all the evill of his
actions upon his evill Councellors,</hi> yet he and his Officers in their
Remonſtrance from St <hi>Albons,</hi> 16. of <hi>November</hi> 1648. ſay
<hi>That the King himſelf is the reall Fountain, and true originall, from
whom principally all that miſchief hath iſſued, that of late in his Raign
hath befaln the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom being himſelf the principall Author, and cauſer of
the firſt and ſecond War, and thereby guilty of all the innocent blood
ſpilt therein, and of all the evils hapning thereby,</hi> pag. 17. 19. 23.
24. 61. 62, 64. <hi>whoſe one example, in doing Juſtice upon, to future
Generations, would be of more terror and avail, then the execution of his whole
party,;</hi> pag. 47. 48. <hi>It being</hi> (as they ſay) <hi>a moſt
unjuſt and unconſcionable thing to puniſh inferior Miniſters, the
acceſſories, and let the King, the principall, go free,</hi> pag. 50.</p>
            <p>Even ſo, though moſt men now lay the blame of all the Armies
apoſtacy, baſeneſs, perfidiouſneſs and treachery upon
<hi>Cromwel</hi> and <hi>Ireton,</hi> as the Generals evil Councellors; yet
they (his Screen betwixt him and the peoples wrath) being gone from him towards
<hi>Ireland,</hi> he will now appear nakedly and ſingly, to be as he is in
himſelf, and let him take heed, leſt from his by-paſt conſtant,
ſigning, aſſenting to, approving of, and acting in all their
perfidiouſneſs, treachery and baſeneſs, with his preſent carriage,
now he ſtands, as it were a Noun Subſtantive, upon his own legs, and may
now moſt gloriouſly act honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and juſtly if he pleaſe, without
their controul or any others (and ſo regain his loſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and
reputation) if wickedneſs and baſeneſs be not as largely inherent in his
heart, as it is in either <hi>Cromwels, or Iretons:</hi> I ſay, let him take
heed from all his actings, the knowing and ſeeing people do not juſtly
conclude him to be the principal Author and cauſer of all their miſeries,
diſtreſſes and woes; <hi>and ſo in time ſerve him, as he hath
ſerved the King.</hi> and only put <hi>Cromwel, Ireton, Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rig, Bradſhaw, Harriſon,
&amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Hambletons, Hollands, Capels, Gorings, and Owens places, as
but acceſſories or depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants upon</hi> Fairfax <hi>the
principall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my true friends, I ſhall hear take upon me the boldneſs
(in regard of the great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions of the preſent times) to give a
little further advice to you, from whoſe compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or ſociety (or from
ſome of them) hath begun, and iſſued out the moſt tranſcendent,
cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar, rational and juſt things
for the peoples Liberties and Freedoms, that I have ſeen or read in this
Nation as your notable and excellent <hi>Petition of May</hi> 20 1647.
<hi>burnt by the hands of the common Hangman,</hi> Recorded in my Book, called
<hi>Raſh Oaths unwarranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, pag.</hi> 29 30, 31, 32, 33, 34 35. with
divers others Petitions of that nature; <hi>and the Petition of the</hi> 19
<hi>of Jan.</hi> 1647. <hi>Recorded in the following diſcourſe, pag.</hi>
45, 46, 47, 48, <hi>&amp;c. and the maſculine Petition of the</hi> 11. <hi>of
Sept:</hi> 1648. <hi>ſo much owned by Petitions out of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Counties,
yea, and by the Officers of the Armies large Remonſtrance from St</hi> Albans
<hi>of the</hi> 16. <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1648. <hi>pag</hi> 67 68, 69. The
ſubſtance of all which, I conceive is contained in the Printed ſheet of
paper ſigned by my fellow priſoners, Mr. <hi>Will. Walwin,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Tho, Prince,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rich. Ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rton, and my ſelf,</hi> dated the 1. of <hi>May.</hi> 1649. and
intituled <hi>An Agreement of the free people of England, &amp;c.</hi> The
principles of which I hope and deſire you will make the final Center, &amp;
unwavering Standard of all your deſires, hazards and indeavors, as to the
future ſettlement of the peace and government of this diſtracted, waſted,
and divided Nation; the firm eſtabliſhing of the principles therein
contained, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing that only, which
will really and in good earneſt marry and knit that intereſt, what ever it
be, that dwells upon them, unto the diſtreſſed, and oppreſſed
Commons, or people of this Nation; yea, the ſetling of which principles, is
that, that will thereby make it evident and apparent unto all rationall and
underſtanding people in the world, that the reall and hearty good and
welfare, of the people of this Nation, hath cordially, and in good earneſt
been that, that their ſouls have hunted for, and thirſted after in all the
late bloody civill wars, and conteſts: <hi>All the Conteſts of the Kings
party for his will and Prerogative, being meerly <pb n="6" facs="tcp:36016:4"/>Selviſh,
and ſo none of the peoples intereſt;</hi> and the conteſt of the
<hi>Presbyterians for their mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-bate, dividing, and hypocriticall Covenant, no better in the
leaſt;</hi> and the preſent conteſt of the preſent diſſembling
intereſt of <hi>Independents</hi> for the peoples Liberties in generall,
(read the following Diſcourſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 27, 28, 29.) meerly no more
but Self in the higheſt <hi>and to ſet up the falſe ſaint, and moſt
deſperate Apoſtate murderer and traytor,</hi> Oliver Cromwel, <hi>by a
pretended election of his mercinary ſouldiers, under the falſe name of the
godly Intereſt, to be King of England, &amp;c.</hi> (that being now too too
apparently; all the intended them by his Will and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leaſure, and ſo deſtroy and
envaſſalize their lives and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to his luſts, which is the
higheſt treaſon that ever was committed or acted in this Nation, in any
ſenſe or kinde; <hi>either firſt, in the eye of the Law, or ſecondly,
in the eye of the ancient</hi> (but yet too much arbitrary) <hi>proceedings of
Parliament, or thirdly, in the eye of their own late declared principles of
reaſon;</hi> by pretence of which (and by no rules of Law in the leaſt)
they took away the late Kings head, and life, which if there were any Law or
Juſtice in <hi>England</hi> to be had, or any Magiſtrates left to execute
it, <hi>(as in the leaſt there is not)</hi> I durſt undertake upon my life,
plainly evidently; and undeniably, <hi>to make good the foreſaid unparalleld
treaſons againſt the foreſaid</hi> Ol. Cromwel, upon, &amp; againſt all
the three forementioned principles, <hi>viz. Law, Parliament,</hi> and
<hi>Reaſon;</hi> yea, and to frame againſt him ſuch an Impeachment, or
Indictment <hi>(which way of Indictments is the true, legall, and only juſt
way of</hi> England <hi>to be tried at the Common Law,</hi> higher and greater
then all the charges, <hi>againſt the fourty four Judges</hi>) <hi>hanged for
falſe and illegal Judgments, by King</hi> Alfred <hi>before the
conqueſt;</hi> which with their crimes, are recorded in the Law Book, called
<hi>The mirror of Juſtice,</hi> Printed in Engliſh, for <hi>Matthew
Walbank</hi> at <hi>Grayes Inn</hi> gate, 1646. <hi>page</hi> 239. 240. 241.
242. 243. 244. 245. See alſo <hi>page</hi> 196. 197. 207. <hi>ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or then the impeachment or accuſation <hi>Of the Lord chief
Juſtice</hi> Wayland, <hi>and the reſt of his brother Judges and Lawyers,
tormented in</hi> Edward <hi>the firſt his time,</hi> and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in
<hi>Speeds</hi> Chronicle, <hi>fol.</hi> 635.</p>
            <p>Or then the impeachment in Parliament, <hi>againſt Judg</hi>
Thorp, <hi>who for taking ſmall bribes againſt his oath, was condemned to
die in</hi> Edward <hi>the third his time;</hi> of whom, you may read in the 3.
<hi>part. Cooks Inſtitut. fol.</hi> 155, 156, and in Mr. <hi>Pyms</hi> Speech
againſt the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> in the Book called <hi>Speeches and
Paſſages of Parliament, pag.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>Or then the impeachment or a charge of the dethroned King
<hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, in full Parliament, the maner of whoſe
dethroning you may notably read in <hi>Speeds</hi> Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle, <hi>fol.</hi>
665.</p>
            <p>Or then the many Articles of impeachment, of the dethroned King
<hi>Richard</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, in full Parliament, recorded at large in the
Chronicles, or Hiſtory of <hi>Will. Martin, fol</hi> 156. 157. 158 159. the
8. 10. 12. 15. 21. Articles of which, I conceive moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, as to the
people, which are extraordinary well worth the reading; for in them the King
himſelf, in thoſe dark days of Popery, is charged <hi>To have perverted the
due courſe of the Law, or Juſtice, and Right; and that he deſtroyed men
by information, without legal examination, or tryal; and that he had declared
the Laws of the Kingdom, were in his own Breſt,</hi> (juſt the ſame thing
do Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> and other mercenary Agents of the Grandees of the Army,
now conſtantly declare of them) <hi>and that by himſelf, and his own
authority</hi> (juſt <hi>Cromwel</hi> and <hi>Ireton</hi> like, onely much
ſhort of them) <hi>he had displaced divers Burgeſſes of the Parliament,
and had placed ſuch other in their rooms, as would better fit and ſerve his
own turn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or then the impeachment of the Lord chief Juſtice <hi>Triſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ian</hi> (who had the worſhip or
honor in <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond his time, in full Parliament, to be
apprehended in the forenoon, and hanged at <hi>Tiburn</hi> in the afternoon)
with his brother Judges, <hi>viz. Ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>horp, Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>knap, Care, Hot,
Burge,</hi> and <hi>Lockton;</hi> or their aſſociates, Sir <hi>Nicholas
Bramble,</hi> Lord <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36016:4"/>Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> Sir <hi>Simon
Burley,</hi> Sir <hi>William Elinham,</hi> Sir <hi>John Salisbury,</hi> Sir
<hi>Thomas Trevit,</hi> Sir <hi>James Bernis,</hi> and Sir <hi>Nicholas
Dodgworth; ſome of whom were deſtroyed and hanged, for ſetting their
hands to Judgments, in ſubverſion of the Law, in advancing the Kings will
above Law;</hi> yea, and one of them baniſhed therefore, <hi>although a
dagger was held to his breſt to compel him thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or then the indictment, <hi>of thoſe two grand and notorious,
traitorly ſubvertors of the Laws and Liberties of</hi> England, Empſon,
<hi>and</hi> Dudley, <hi>Privy Counſellors to</hi> Henry <hi>the
ſeventh</hi> recorded in <hi>Cooks</hi> 4. <hi>part. Inſtitut. fol.</hi>
198. 199. read alſo <hi>fol</hi> 41. <hi>ibid.</hi> and 2. <hi>part.
Inſtit. fol.</hi> 51.</p>
            <p>Or then the impeachment of that notorious, wicked, and traiterous
man, Cardinal <hi>Woolſey,</hi> by King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight his Privy
Councel, recorded in the 4. <hi>part. Cooks Inſtit. fol.</hi> 89. 90. 91. 92.
93. 94. 95. Read eſpecially Artic. 17. 20. 21. 23. 25. 26. 30. 31. 33. 35.
38. 42. in all which, he is charged <hi>with Arbitrarineſs, and
ſubverſion of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or then the impeachment of the Shipmoney Judges, <hi>who in one
judgment did as much as in them lay, deſtroy all the Properties of all the
men in</hi> England; read the notable Speeches againſt them, in Speeches, and
Paſſages.</p>
            <p>Or then the impeachment of the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in
the late Parliament.</p>
            <p>Or then the impeachment, <hi>of the Lord Keeper</hi> Finch,
<hi>Earl of</hi> Strafford, <hi>Secretary</hi> Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debank, <hi>Sir</hi> Richard
Bolton, <hi>Lord Chancellor of</hi> Ireland, John <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi>
Derry, <hi>Sir</hi> Gerrard Lowther, <hi>Knight, Lord chief Juſtice of the
Common Pleas in</hi> Ireland, <hi>and Sir</hi> George Ratcliff, all whoſe
impeachments are recorded in a Book, intituled, <hi>Speeches and Paſſages
of Parliament, from November,</hi> 1640. 10 <hi>June,</hi> 1641. <hi>Pag.</hi>
76. 77. <hi>to</hi> 83. <hi>and</hi> 117. 118. <hi>to</hi> 143. <hi>and</hi>
174. <hi>and</hi> 256. 257. 258.</p>
            <p>Or then the Articles or charge <hi>againſt the two Sir</hi> John
Hothams; the elder of which, kept the King out of <hi>Hull,</hi> the beginning
of theſe Wars, <hi>when the Houſe of Commons durſt not command him
poſitively to do it, although they were effectually put upon it, by a motion
from the younger, then ſitting in the Houſe;</hi> and yet they were both
beheaded as Traytors, for but endevoring to betray <hi>Hull</hi> to the
King.</p>
            <p>Or then the late impeachment <hi>of Sir</hi> Philip Stapleton,
<hi>Maſter</hi> Denzil Hollis, <hi>and the reſt of the eleven Members,</hi>
whoſe impeachment of high Treaſon, is recorded in the Armies Book of
Declarations, <hi>pag.</hi> 47. <hi>to</hi> 50. <hi>and pag.</hi> 94 95. 96.
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet the ſame things, that ſome of them, in a capital
maner, were impeached for as Traytors, their impeachers acted, and did at the
very ſelf-ſame time, as is clearly declared in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
diſcourſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 31. 32. <hi>to</hi> 39. <hi>and page</hi> 53.
<hi>to</hi> 62.</p>
            <p>Yea, or then the impeachment of King <hi>Charls, whom</hi> Cromwel
<hi>and</hi> Ireton <hi>principally</hi> (<hi>Bradſhaw</hi> being but their
hired mercinary ſlave) <hi>have beheaded for a Tyrant and Traytor;</hi>
whoſe impeachment is recorded in the following diſcourſe, <hi>page</hi>
65. 66. 67.</p>
            <p>But the principles of the foreſaid <hi>Agreement,</hi> being
ſo deteſtable and abominable to the preſent ruling men, as that which
they know will put a full end to their tyranny and uſurpation, and really
eaſe and free the people from oppreſſion and bondage; that it is
ſomething dangerous to thoſe that go about the promotion of it; yet I
ſhall adviſe and exhort you vigorouſly, to lay all fear aſide, and to
ſet on foot the promotion of it, in the ſame method we took for the
promotion of the foreſaid Petition of the 19 <hi>of January,</hi> 1647. laid
down in the following diſcourſe, <hi>page</hi> 23. 24. 25. And write to
your friends in every Country of <hi>England to chuſe out from amongſt
themſelves, and ſend up ſome Agents to you</hi> (two at leaſt, from
each County, with money in their pockets to bear their charges) <hi>to
conſider with your culd and choſen Agents, of ſome effectual courſe
ſpeedily to be taken, for the ſetling the principles thereof</hi> (as that
onely within an earthly Government, can make you happy) <hi>or at leaſt, to
know one anothers mindes, in owning and approving the principles thereof;</hi>
that ſo it may become to you, and all your friends, <hi>your Center,
Standard, and <pb n="8" facs="tcp:36016:5"/>Banner, to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ock together to, in the time of
thoſe forraign invaſions, and domeſtick inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that are like
ſpeedily to bring miſeries enough upon this poor and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtreſſed Nation,</hi> and unanimouſly reſolve
&amp; engage <hi>one to another, neither to ſide with, or fight for the
Cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oes, fooleries, and pride of the
preſent men in power, nor for the Prince his will, or any other baſe
intereſt whatſeover</hi> (the which, if you ſhould fight for, it would be
but an abſolute murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your Brethren and Countrymen, you know not
wherefore) <hi>unleſs he, or they will come up to thoſe juſt, righteous,
and equitable principles therein contained, and give rational, and good
ſecurity, for the conſtant adhering thereunto;</hi> and upon ſuch terms,
I do not ſee, but you may juſtifiably, before God or man, Joyn with the
Prince himſelf (yea, I am ſure a thouſand times more juſtly, then the
preſent ruling men (upon a large and ſerious debate) joyned with <hi>Owen
Roe O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eal; the grand bloody rebell
in Ireland</hi>) who if we muſt have a King, I for my part had rather have
the Prince, then any man in the world, becauſe of his large pretence of
Right, which if he come not in by Conqueſt, by the hands of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigners (the
bare attempting of which may apparently hazard him the loſs of all at once,
by gluing together the now divided people to joyn as one man againſt him) but
by the hands of Engliſhmen, by contract, upon the principles aforeſaid
(which is eaſie to be done) the people will eaſily ſee that preſently
thereupon, they will injoy this tranſcendent benefit (he being at peace with
all forraign Nations, and having no regall pretended Competitor) <hi>viz. the
immediate disbanding of all Armies, and Garriſons, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the old
Cinque-ports, and ſo thoſe three grand plagues of the people will
ceaſe,</hi> viz. <hi>Free-quarter, Taxations, and Exciſe,</hi> by means of
which, the people may once again really ſay, they injoy ſomething they can
in good earneſt call their own; <hi>whereas, for the preſent Army to ſet
up the pretended falſe Saint</hi> Oliver (or any other) <hi>as their elected
King,</hi> there will be nothing thereby from the beginning of the Chapter to
the end thereof, <hi>but Wars, and the cutting of throats year after year;</hi>
yea, and the abſolute keeping up of a perpetuall and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Army
under which the people are abſolute and perfect ſlaves, and vaſſals, as
by woful and lamentable experience they now ſee, they perfectly are, which
ſlavery and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute bondage is like daily to increaſe, <hi>under the
preſent tyrannicall and arbritrary new erected robbing Government;</hi> And
therefore rouze up your ſpirits before it be too late, to a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
promotion, and ſetling of the principles of the foreſaid Agreement, as the
onely ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and perfect means to cure you of all your maladies and
diſtempers: So with my hearty and true love preſented to all that remain
upright amongſt you (without being perverted to Apoſtacy by the pretended
Councell of States places or bribes) I commit you to the ſafe tuition and
protection of the moſt high, the <hi>Lord Jehovah, and Almighty,</hi> and
re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute> 
               <signed>Yours and the Nations faithful, hearty, reſolved friend,
and ſervant in the midſt of all adverſity, afflictions, trials, and
ſorrows (that never more in all my life incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed me round about then
now) till death, JOHN LILBURN.</signed> 
               <dateline>From my unjuſt and illegall
(though contented) captivity, for my honeſty and innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and nothing
elſe (as to man) in cloſe impriſonment, in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi>
without any legall and juſt allowance of maintenance, 
<date>this preſent 17. of July, 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
